So, I'm going to start off with kind of the buzzkill a little bit.
حسنا، سأبدأ بشيء مرعب قليلا.
Forty-two million people
42 مليون شخص
were displaced by natural disasters in 2010.
أصبحوا مشردين بسبب الكوارث الطيبيعية سنة 2010.
Now, there was nothing particularly special about 2010,
الآن، مامن شيء مثير للاهتمام بشأن سنة 2010،
because, on average, 31 and a half million people
لأن المعدل يرتفع ل 31 ونصف مليون شخص
are displaced by natural disasters every single year.
مشرد بسبب الكوارث الطبيعية كل عام.
Now, usually when people hear statistics or stats like that,
حسنا، عادة عندما يسمع الناس عن إحصائيات أو وقائع كهذه،
you start thinking about places like Haiti or other kind of
يمكنك أن تفكر في أماكن مثل هايتي أو مناطق
exotic or maybe even impoverished areas, but it happens
أخرى ليست بالمألوفة، أو حتى مناطق فقيرة، لكن هذا يحدث
right here in the United States every single year.
هنا في الولايات المتحدة كل عام.
Last year alone, 99 federally declared disasters
في العام الماضي فقط، تم الإعلان عن 99 كارثة طبيعية من طرف الحكومة الفيدرالية
were on file with FEMA,
على قائمة الوكالة الأمريكية لإدارة الطوارىء،
from Joplin, Missouri, and Tuscaloosa, Alabama,
من جوبلين ،ميسوري ، و توسكالوزا، ألاباما،
to the Central Texas wildfires that just happened recently.
إلى وسط تكساس حيث وقعت حرائق الغابات مؤخرا.
Now, how does the most powerful country in the world
السؤال الآن هو، كيف تتعامل أقوى دولة في العالم
handle these displaced people?
مع المشردين من جراء الكوارث الطبيعية؟
They cram them onto cots, put all your personal belongings
تكدسهم على أسِرَة صغيرة وتضع جميع ممتلكاتك الشخصية
in a plastic garbage bag, stick it underneath,
في كيس بلاستيكي ،تضعه أسفل منك ،
and put you on the floor of an entire sports arena,
وتضعك على الأرض في ملعب رياضي،
or a gymnasium.
أو صالة رياضة.
So obviously there's a massive housing gap,
إذن فإنه من الواضح أن هناك فجوة كبيرة في مجال الأيواء،
and this really upset me, because academia tells you
وهذا أمر يزعجني فعلا، لأنه أكاديميا،
after a major disaster, there's typically about
بعد كارثة طبيعية كبيرة ، يستلزم الأمر عادة،
an 18-month time frame to -- we kinda recover,
18 شهرا لكي تعود الأمور إلى طبيعتها،
start the recovery process,
وتبدأ عملية إعادة الإعمار،
but what most people don't realize is that on average
لكن مالا يدركه الأغلبية من الناس أنه في المتوسط
it takes 45 to 60 days or more
يتطلب الأمر من 45 إلى 60 يوما إضافيا
for the infamous FEMA trailers to even begin to show up.
للوكالة الفيدرالية لإدارة الطوارئ لكي تظهر و تبدأ في العمل.
Before that time, people are left to their own devices.
قبل هذا الوقت ، يجد الناس أنفسهم أمام واقع يجب عليهم أن يتدبروا الأمر بأنفسهم .
So I became obsessed with trying to figure out a way
لذا أصبحت مهووسا بمحاولة إيجاد طريقة ما
to actually fill this gap.
لسد هذه الفجوة.
This actually became my creative obsession.
أصبح هذا الأمر هوسي المبدع.
I put aside all my freelance work after hours and started
تركت عملي الحر جانبا لساعات ، و بدأت
just focusing particularly on this problem.
التركيز فقط على هذا الأمر.
So I started sketching.
فبدأت بوضع مسودة أولية.
Two days after Katrina, I started sketching and sketching
يومين بعد كارثة كاترينا، بدأت أرسم و أرسم
and trying to brainstorm up ideas or solutions for this,
وبدأت أحاول إيجاد أفكار و حلول لهذا الأمر.
and as things started to congeal or ideas started to form,
وفي الوقت الذي بدأت فيه الأمور تتضح و الأفكار تتشكل ،
I started sketching digitally on the computer,
بدأت أرسم رقميا على الحاسوب ،
but it was an obsession, so I couldn't just stop there.
لكن الأمر استحوذ علي فلم أستطع التوقف عند هذا الحد.
I started experimenting, making models,
فبدأت بالتجربة ، صنع نماذج،
talking to experts in the field, taking their feedback,
بالتحدث إلى الخبراء في هذا المجال ،و أخذ آرائهم،
and refining, and I kept on refining and refining
و التنقيح ، فعكفت على صقل فكرتي و تنقيحها
for nights and weekends for over five years.
لليال، و عطل نهايات الأسبوع، على مدى 5 سنوات.
Now, my obsession ended up driving me to create
الآن، انتهى بي هوسي إلى أن صنعت
full-size prototypes in my own backyard — (Laughter) —
نموذج حقيقي في الحديقة الخلفية لمنزلي --(ضحك)--
and actually spending my own personal savings on
وصرف كل مدخراتي الخاصة على
everything from tooling to patents
شراء الأدوات و تسجيل براء ات الاختراع
and a variety of other costs,
ومجموعة من النفقات المختلفة الأخرى،
but in the end I ended up with this modular housing system
لكن في نهاية الأمر استطعت صنع نظام وحدات إسكانية
that can react to any situation or disaster.
الذي يمكن أن يتناسب مع أي حالة أو كارثة طبيعية.
It can be put up in any environment,
إذ يمكن وضعها في أي بيئة
from an asphalt parking lot to pastures or fields,
من موقف سيارات إسفلتي ، إلى المراعي و الحقول،
because it doesn't require any special setup
لأنه لا يتطلب تركيبا خاصا،
or specialty tools.
أو أدوات خاصة.
Now, at the foundation and kind of the core
الآن، أساس و جوهر
of this whole system is the Exo Housing Unit,
هذا النظام كله نظام (EXO) إيكسو للوحدات السكنية،
which is just the individual shelter module.
والذي هو عبارة عن وحدة سكنية فردية.
And though it's light, light enough that you can actually
ورغم أنها خفيفة، خفيفة لدرجة أنه يمكنك
lift it by hand and move it around,
رفعها باليد وتحريكها،
and it actually sleeps four people.
يمكن أن ينام داخلها 4 أشخاص.
And you can arrange these things as kind of more
ويمكنك ترتيب هذه الأمور بطرق متنوعة أخرى
for encampments and more of a city grid type layout,
على شكل معسكرات ، أو على شكل شبيه بمخطط شبكة المدينة،
or you can circle the wagons, essentially,
أو يمكنك وضع الوحدات على شكل دائري، بالأساس،
and form these circular pods out of them,
وتشكيل هذه الدوائر منها،
which give you this semi-private communal area
مما يعطيكم منطقة تجمع شبه خاصة
for people to actually spill out into so they're not actually
حتى يشعر الناس براحة أكبر
trapped inside these units.
و ليس بأنهم محاصرون داخل هذه الوحدات.
Now this fundamentally changes
هذا الأمر يغير في الأساس
the way we respond to disasters,
طريقة تجاوبنا مع الكوارث،
because gone are the horrid conditions
فقد ولت الظروف الفظيعة
inside a sports arena or a gymnasium, where people
داخل القاعات الرياضية ،حيث يتكدس
are crammed on these cots inside.
الناس على أسرة صغيرة داخلها.
Now we have instant neighborhoods outside.
الآن تتشكل لدينا أحياء بشكل تلقائي.
So the Exo is designed to be simply, basically
لذلك ف 'الإكسو" مصمم ببساطة، بالأساس
like a coffee cup. They can actually stack together
مثل كأس القهوة، يمكننا في الواقع أن نجمعها معا
so we get extremely efficient transportation
لنحصل على عملية غاية في الفعالية في ما يخص النقل
and storage out of them.
و التخزين.
In fact, 15 Exos can fit on a single semi truck by itself.
حيث أنه بالإمكان وضع 15 وحدة من "إكسو" داخل شاحنة واحدة.
This means the Exo can actually be transported and set up
مما يعني أنه يمكن نقل "إكسو" ونصبها
faster than any other housing option available today.
بشكل أسرع من أي حل إيوائي متوفر اليوم.
But I'm obsessive, so I couldn't just stop there,
لكنني كثير الهوس، لذلك لم أستطع التوقف عند هذا الحد،
so I actually started modifying the bunks where you could
فبدأت بتغيير الأِسّرة ، بحيث يمكنك
actually slide out the bunks and slide in desks or shelving,
أن تخرج الأسِرَّة و تدخل مكانها مكتبا أو رفوفا،
so the same unit can now be used
فيصبح بالإمكان استعمال نفس الوحدة
for an office or storage location.
كمكتب أو وحدة تخزين.
The doors can actually swap out, so you can actually put on
يمكن للأبواب أن تُنزع ،و يمكنك أن تضع مكانها
a rigid panel with a window unit in it for climate control,
لوحا صلبا به نافذة للتحكم في الحرارة،
or a connector module that would allow you to actually
أو وحدة موصلة تمكنك
connect multiple units together, which gives you
من ربط عدة وحدات مع بعضها ،مما يعطيك
larger and kind of compartmentalized living spaces,
فضاء عيش أوسع مكون من عدة أجزاء،
so now this same kit of parts, this same unit
الآن ، يمكن استخدام نفس الطقم من الأجزاء، ونفس الوحدات
can actually serve as a living room, bedroom or bathroom,
كغرفة للمعيشة، غرفة نوم ، أو حمام،
or an office, a living space and secure storage.
أو مكتب أو فراغ(مساحة) للعيش ، أو وحدة تخزين آمنة.
Sounds like a great idea, but how do you make it real?
تبدو فكرة رائعة، لكن كيف يمكن جعلها حقيقية ؟
So the first idea I had, initially, was just
كانت الفكرة الأولى التي حضرتني، في البداية، فقط
to go the federal and state governments and go,
أن أذهب إلى الحكومات الفدرالية و أن أقول لهم :
"Here, take it, for free."
" تفضلوا خذوها ، بالمجان"
But I was quickly told that, "Boy, our government
لكنني سرعان ماقلت في نفسي :"يا رجل ، حكوماتنا
doesn't really work like that." (Laughter)
لا تعمل بهذا الشكل "( ضحك)
Okay. Okay. So maybe I would start a nonprofit
حسنا ، حسنا ، ربما علي أن أن أنشأ مؤسسة غير ربحية
to kind of help consult and get this idea going
بغرض الاستشارة، وجعل هذه الفكرة تتبلور
along with the government, but then I was told,
مع العمل جنبا إلي جنب مع الحكومة ،لكنه قيل لي ،
"Son, our government looks to private sector
" يا ابني، الحكومة تنظرإلى القطاع الخاص
for things like this."
في مثل هذه الأمور."
Okay. So maybe I would take this whole idea and go
حسنا، قلت ربما علي أن آخذ الفكرة برمتها
to private corporations that would have this mutually shared
وأذهب بها إلى الشركات الخاصة التي لها نفس الاهتمام المشترك
benefit to it, but I was quickly told by some corporations
لكنه سرعان ما قيل لي من طرف بعض الشركات
that my personal passion project was not a brand fit
أن مشروعي الخاص الطموح غير مناسب للعلامات التجارية
because they didn't want their logos stamped
لأنهم لا يريدون وضع شعار شركاتهم
across the ghettos of Haiti.
في أحياء معزولة في هايتي.
Now, I wasn't just obsessed. I was outraged. (Laughter.)
هذه المرة لم أكن مهووسا، بل مستشيط الغضب.(ضحك)
So I decided, kind of told myself,
لذا قررت ، وقلت لنفسي ،
"Oh yeah? Watch this. I'll do it myself." (Laughter)
"حسنا، راقب ماسأفعل، سأقوم بهذا الأمر بنفسي" (ضحك)
Now, this quickly, my day job sent me to work out of
بعدها بسرعة أرسلتني الشركة التي أعمل بها نهارا لكي أعمل من
our Milan office for a few months, so I was like,
مكتبنا في ميلانو ،لبضعة أشهر، فتساءلت،
what will I do? So I actually scheduled sleep on my calendar,
ماذا سأفعل؟ فبدأت بضبط مواعيد نومي على مذكرتي التقويمية،
and spent the 8-hour time difference on conference calls
وكنت أقضي ساعات الفرق الثمانية في محادثات هاتفية
with material suppliers, manufacturers and potential customers.
مع موردي المواد ، مصنعين، و زبائن محتملين.
And we found through this whole process, we found
فوجدنا من خلال هذه العملية ، وجدنا
this great little manufacturer in Virginia,
هذا المصنع الصغير الرائع في ولاية فيرجينيا،
and if his body language is any indication,
وإذا كانت لغة جسده تعطي أية إشارة،
that's the owner — (Laughter) — of what it's like
هذا هو مالك المصنع --( ضحك)-- عن
for a manufacturer to work directly with a designer,
كيفية العمل المباشر بين المصنِع و المصمم،
you've got to see what happens here. (Laughter)
عليكم أن تروا ما يحصل هنا. ( ضحك)
But G.S. Industries was fantastic.
لكن بي جي للصناعات رائعة جدا.
They actually built three prototypes for us by hand.
إذ صمموا لنا ثلاثة نماذج أولية يدويا.
So now we have prototypes that can show that four people
إذن لدينا الآن نموذج أولي يرينا أنه بإمكان 4 أشخاص
can actually sleep securely and much more comfortably
أن يناموا بشكل آمن و براحة كبيرة
than a tent could ever provide.
لا يمكن لأي خيمة أن توفرها .
And they actually shipped them here to Texas for us.
وقد قاموا بشحنها و إيصالها لنا هنا في تكساس.
Now, a funny thing started happening.
والآن أمر مضحك بدأ يحدث.
Other people started to believe in what we were doing,
بدأ أناس آخرون يؤمنون بما نقوم به،
and actually offered us hangar space, donated hangar
في الحقيقة ،عرضوا علينا حظيرة للطائرات،
space to us. And then the Georgetown Airport Authority
تبرعوا بها(حظيرة الطائرات) لنا .وبعدها عزمت إدارة مطار جورج تاون
was bent over backwards to help us with anything we needed.
على مساعدتنا بأي شيء نحتاجه.
So now we had a hangar space to work in,
فحصلنا على حظيرة للطائرات لنعمل بها،
and prototypes to demo with.
ونماذج أولية من أجل العرض.
So in one year, we've negotiated manufacturing agreements,
وخلال عام واحد، تفاوضنا على اتفاقيات تصنيع،
been awarded one patent, filed our second patent,
تم منحنا براءة اختراع ، وقدمنا طلبا للحصول على براءة اختراع ثانية،
talked to multiple people, demoed this to FEMA
تحدثنا إلى مجموعة من الأشخاص، قدمنا عرضا للوكالة الفيدرالية لإدارة الطوارئ
and its consultants to rave reviews,
ومستشاريها بشكل شيق،
and then started talking to some other people who requested
وبعدها بدأنا التحدث إلى أناس طلبوا
information, this little group called the United Nations.
معلومات منا ، و هذه المجموعة الصغيرة تدعى الأمم المتحدة.
And on top of that, now we have
وعلاوة على ذلك، لدينا الآن
a whole plethora of other individuals that have come up
مجموعة كبيرة من الأفراد الآخرين الذين جاؤوا
and started to talk to us from doing it for mining camps,
للتحدث إلينا عن استعمال منتجاتنا من معسكرات المناجم ،
mobile youth hostels, right down to the World Cup
بيوت الشباب المتنقلة، وصولا إلى كأس العالم
and the Olympics.
والألعاب الأولمبية.
So, in closing, on this whole thing here
وفي النهاية، ما أتمناه بخصوص هذا الأمر كله
is hopefully very soon we will not have to
ألا نكون مضطرين في القريب العاجل
respond to these painful phone calls that we get
إلى استقبال تلك المكالمات الهاتفية المؤلمة
after disasters where we don't really have anything
التي تصلنا بعد وقوع الكوارث الطبيعية حيث لا نجد فعلا ما يمكننا
to sell or give you yet.
بيعه أو حتى إعطاءه لكم.
Hopefully very soon we will be there,
آمل في القريب العاجل أن نكون هناك،
because we are destined,
لأن قدرنا أن نكون ،
obsessed with making it real.
مهووسين بجعل الأفكار حقيقة ملموسة.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا (تصفيق)